<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A compendious prologue, or Epilogue to the duply-tripartite-patheticall, unpublished studies (animadvertory, suppeditatory, to the Kings Majesty, his dominions and adherents) of J.T. (a hearty wel-willer to his King and conntry [sic]) since the incursion of these intestine wars, &amp;c. being a conservatory dilation, and cordiall application, to the use and advantage of all in all.</title>
            <author>J. T.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62818</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T17</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219146</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830665</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830665</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35118</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62818)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35118)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2080:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A compendious prologue, or Epilogue to the duply-tripartite-patheticall, unpublished studies (animadvertory, suppeditatory, to the Kings Majesty, his dominions and adherents) of J.T. (a hearty wel-willer to his King and conntry [sic]) since the incursion of these intestine wars, &amp;c. being a conservatory dilation, and cordiall application, to the use and advantage of all in all.</title>
                  <author>J. T.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:35118:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 37 -->
            <head>A compendious Prologue, or Epilogue, to the duply-tripartite-patheticall, unpub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed ſtudies (animadvertory, ſuppeditatory, to the Kings Majeſty, his Dominions and Adherents) of <hi>J. T.</hi> (a hearty wel-willer to his King and Country) ſince the incurſion of theſe inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine wars, &amp;c. Being a conſervatory dilation, and cordiall applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to the uſe and advantage of all in all.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dread Soveraigne,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THeſe labours of your loyall reall Subject, as they were at firſt undertaken, ſo have they been proſecuted, chiefly for your Majeſties and Kingdomes good; by which your Majeſty eſpecially (and many others) are premoniſhed and ſummoned in entire affection, (if you will at laſt) to work out your owne, and your Subjects (commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to your charge) good, by yet honourable, diſcreet, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall returne and reſidence with your faithfull, fairely, firſt elected, and often acknowledged Parliament: It was the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and underſtanding, nay, the righteouſneſſe of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Iſrael, to obſerve and doe the Statutes and judgements the Lord commanded them by the hand of <hi>Moſes,</hi> for their good: In the opinion of your Subjects generally (dread So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne) it is your beſt, wiſeſt courſe in the ſight of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which ſhall heare thereof, thus to returne. Doe it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally dread Soveraigne; adviſe to, and act it (God enable you) Nobles and Gentlemen: The learned ſay <hi>acts agimus;</hi> God that made us without our ſelves, will not ſave us with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out our ſelves: There is no peace nor good to be expected in <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. till every man doe his duty, diſcharge his place: As the Parliament (I take it) have continually performed
<pb facs="tcp:35118:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->their parts, ſo (dread Soveraigne, excuſe my humble ſubju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall boldneſſe) it concernes your candid Majeſty to diſcharge yours. O God enable all: If thre be a willing mind, what can hinder? <hi>Abraham</hi> would not contend with <hi>Lot</hi> his inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, but gave him the preheminence: The Parliament are againe preparing Propoſitions; if there be not a reall gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall compliance, doubtleſſe the juſt God will (whenſoever) take vengeance: Tremble, ſtand in awe, whoſoever it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes (eſpecially thoſe that ſhall but goe about to ſtop this work from the Kings Majeſty, his eare, his eye, or both; or from any other it neceſſarily or hopefully concernes for the publike good) ſinne not againſt <hi>Englands,</hi> &amp;c. preſent peace, and your own future good; the great King that is placed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the holy hill of Sion, will certainly break the thus abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, conſcience telling, ſtill repugners to peace (he hath had them in deriſion all this while) with a rod of iron, and daſh them in pieces like a Potters veſſell; <hi>Be wiſe now therefore O ye Kings, be inſtructed ye Nobles,</hi> &amp;c. Gods wrath is not a little kindled, his plagues and vengeance will abſolutely fall heavy ſomewhere (where is the fault) if there be no remedy.</p>
            <p>This the following labours are (no Epitheſis, but) in every part full of love and reall perſwaſion to a bleſſed, by all much to be deſired and endeavoured, Peace; nay, ſo full of (truly columbine) reduplication and repetitory ingemination; that truly you may eſteem them nonſenſe, loquacity: But yet take heed, in this vaſt, civill breach, be not ſo uncivill to judge ſo; the ſchoole of Heaven may, will admit of Totologies, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in ſuch a caſe, ſuch a time as this is.</p>
            <p>If thou canſt (I wiſh thee for thy good, doe it) find oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity hereby (by theſe poor equanimall inculcations) to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit thy ſelfe, thy Country, honour thy God; doe it, thou ſhalt well ſatisfie thy loyall hearty Suppliant; pleaſe thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, if you conſent, juſt, righteous dealing, if you refuſe, God: We ought to do (eſpecially in ſuch a buſineſſe as this) that which is wel-pleaſing and acceptable to God. The whole current of the Scriptures denounce and publiſh many bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings to the obedient, curſes of all ſorts to the diſobedient, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. <hi>Levit</hi> 26. chapters eſpecially.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:35118:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->
               <label>Deut. 4. 25, 26.</label>
               <lb/>
When thou ſhalt beget children, and childrens children, and ſhalt have remained long in the Land, and ſhall corrupt your ſelves, and make a graven Image, or the likeneſſe of any thing, and ſhall doe evill in the ſight of the Lord thy God, to provoke him to anger; I call Heaven and earth to witneſſe againſt you this day, that you ſhall ſoon utterly periſh from off the Land whereunto you goe over Jordan to poſſeſſe it; you ſhall not prolong your dayes upon it, but ſhall utterly be deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Deut. 1. 43, 44.</label>
               <lb/>
I ſpake unto you, and you would not heare; but rebelled againſt the Commandement of the Lord, and went preſumptuously up into the hill.</p>
            <p>And the Amorites which dwelt in that Mountaine, came out againſt you, and chaſed you as Bees doe, and deſtroyed you in <hi>Seir</hi> even unto <hi>Hormah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Joſh. 11. 20.</label>
               <lb/>
It was of the Lord to harden their hearts, that they ſhould come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Iſrael in battell, that he might deſtroy them utterly, and that they might have no favour; but that he might deſtroy them as the Lord commanded <hi>Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>2 Chron. 25. 15, 16.</label>
               <lb/>
Wherefore the anger of the Lord was kindled againſt <hi>Amaziah,</hi> and he ſent unto him a Prophet, which ſaid unto him, why haſt thou ſought after the gods of the people, which could not deliver their owne people out of thine hand.</p>
            <p>And it came to paſſe as he talked with him, that the King ſaid unto him, art thou made of the Kings Counſell? forbeare, why ſhouldeſt thou be ſmitten? Then the Prophet forbare and ſaid, I know that God hath determined (for it came of God, <hi>ver. 20.</hi>) to deſtroy thee, becauſe thou haſt done this, and haſt not hearkned unto my Counſell.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Zeph. 3. 5.</label>
               <lb/>
Every morning the Lord bringeth his judgements to light, he faileth not; but the wicked will not (the ingenuous, pious will) learne to be aſhamed; the unjuſt knoweth no ſhame.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Pſal. 9. 20.</label>
               <lb/>
Put them in feare, O Lord, that they may know themſelves to be but men, <hi>Selah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Deut. 12. 28.</label>
               <lb/>
Obſerve all theſe words which I command thee, that it may goe well
<pb facs="tcp:35118:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->with thee, and with thy children after thee for ever, when thou doſt that which is juſt and right in the ſight of the Lord thy God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Luke 16. 31.</label>
               <lb/>
If they heare not Moſes and the Prophets, neither will they be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded though one roſe from the dead.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Tit. 2. 7, 8.</label>
               <lb/>
In all things ſhewing thy ſelfe a patterne of good works, in doctrine, ſhewing uncorruptneſſe, gravity, ſincerity.</p>
            <p>Sound ſpeech that cannot be condemned, that he that is of the contrary part may be aſhamed, having no evill thing to ſay of you.</p>
            <p>
               <label>2 Tim. 2. 7.</label>
               <lb/>
Conſider what I ſay, and the Lord give thee underſtanding in all things.</p>
            <p>
               <label>ver. 15.</label>
               <lb/>
Study to ſhew thy ſelfe approved unto God, a workman that needeth not to be aſhamed, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
